It's not about the competition.
It's not about following the script.
It's not about editing by numbers.
It's not about
...out-of-the-box thinking.
It is
...neither about this.
It is about putting one shot next to the other
...and start getting ideas.
What matters is what happened to you
...in those hours you spend making something work.
Even if you didn't win,
...even if you didn't submit,
...as long as you did the work,
...you get something out of this challenge
...that is truly epic.
You like this?
That's pretty cool, huh?
Welcome.
I just wanted to share with you that
...we've gone through all the submissions
...of the Epic Editing Challenge.
And in this video,
...I'm gonna let you know who're the winners.
But I'm also gonna share with you
...some feedback, some advice, and some takeaways
...that are not only relevant to the
people that actually submit it,
...but also those that are just watching.
The Epic Editing Challenge is a collab
...with this guy, Kris Truini.
I'm gonna go to him later to present my ideas
...of who I think should win this thing,
...and he's gonna have his top picks.
So I'm basically sitting here on my bed
...reviewing all the cuts.
In the first round,
...what we're gonna do is we're
gonna divide and conquer.
Anything that is above a certain score
...we're both gonna look at.
We're not really trying to, like,
...judge each one and give it the right score.
We just want to find the best of the best
...as efficiently as possible.
If we take a look at the score card over here,
...I cannot see
...whose video this is.
And there are five categories:
Storytelling,
...technical execution,
...transitions,
...uniqueness,
...and overall engagement.
These are the ones Chris is scoring.
Then we have these links to these videos.
See what happens?
Your video, the scene that you cut and uploaded,
...shows up here.
I can't really see who you are.
I'll just start watching a scene like this
...and we'll start judging this video.
I really want to see what you do with what you have,
...and how you can turn that in
a story that works on its own.
Should I just show you one that I really liked?
23.5
Still in the running.
Chris, if he gives it a perfect score,
...this might still win.
Let's just take a peek
...at why I thought this deserves such a high score:
There's some effects there that I like,
...but I'm sure that's not the sole
reason why I like this video.
Aha.
So there's some internal thoughts going on.
There's something nice about the pacing.
...or how much time we take with these moments.
I'll let Chris have a look at this one as well.
And then hopefully it's gonna make it really, really far.
I'm rooting for you.
Having breakfast.
And I'm watching more films.
There's so many of them.
But I wanted to share with everybody
...some of the takeaways.
I made some notes of
...specific videos that are like-
Actually, I'm gonna make a video on The Collective,
...where I look at these examples specifically
...and give some feedback:
Stuff that I like,
...good examples of storytelling...
Right,
There's a- there's an image.
Should I just describe what I see on the screen?
Lots of stylized ones.
Horror style...
Ghosts...
Good uses of voiceover.
"...that yesterday"
"...is but today's memory,"
"...and tomorrow is today's dream."
"We can pretend that doesn't exist."
[engine starting]
Good sound design.
[engine revving, music playing from radio]
After seeing hundreds and hundreds of these scenes...
Building a sound design that makes a big difference.
It makes me feel like I'm in the moment.
I'm experiencing it as it happened.
I think even more important is having
a dynamic range with the scene,
...so a change of pace really helps.
If you use the same piece of music
throughout the entire scene
...and it has the same feel throughout,
...it's really hard to emotionally
...stay engaged throughout.
The importance of ellipses.
Ellipses basically means
...'taking certain things out',
...especially with The Ever After.
I don't think this scene justifies
...going through the entire process.
Now, if you keep me engaged, yes.
BUT
...I really wanted to see
...somebody go in as an editor
...and decide what are the gold moments.
What's important for me to know?
"There're other options."
"Really?"
"Yeah."
"We could just..."
"We could pretend that didn't exist."
"Or..."
"What if we could just be in the present moment?"
Because if you leave things out,
...you're giving the audience
...the opportunity to put it together in their head,
...and they could be more involved with the scene.
That's a big one.
Compression of time to magnify and
make the moments more authentic,
...instead of editing by numbers.
The cutting can really reflect the state of the actors.
I have to say to the vast majority,
...you are taking this scene
...and you're trying to do justice to it.
You're trying to honor what the original
intended of the script or the performance.
But in real life, for me as an editor,
...I really need to take these building blocks
...and I have to turn them into a story
...that engages an audience.
And here's what I'm gonna do.
I'm gonna show my scene
...the way that I cut it originally in the movie.
I'm gonna put that on Patreon.
If you're interested, you can take a look at it.
This is, uh, kind of a rookie mistake.
I shouldn't say that,
...it's arrogant.
I apologize.
I did see quite a bit of people
had found a cool piece of music
...and it has a certain beat to it.
And it motivated them to cut,
...especially in Timeless.
What happens is,
...if I watch it and the audience as well
...and recognize that pattern how you cut,
...my brain is immediately gonna anticipate the next cut,
...and that makes it very predictable,
...and that makes it in a way a little boring.
Everything I say here is like,
...take it with a grain of salt.
It doesn't mean these are the ultimate rules,
...it's just how I feel.
The most important part is
...telling a story beyond the primary layer
...of what's going on in the scene.
That will set you apart.
So there are...
...two or three that I really found that
I'm gonna fight really strongly
for
They did that.
They took the footage
...and they found some subtext
beyond what's on the screen,
...and they start telling the story.
Radio Sound: Did you use the new codes for the ignition explosion?
See what he came up with,
...then we're gonna fight for the winner.
Peace.
SVEN: Yes, I can see you have a spreadsheet up there.
Yeah, it looks pretty good.
You have your camera out there.
Hello.
KRIS: Let's actually show them
...how much work this was
...and how many submissions.
It's like this endless
...spreadsheet of doom.
Whenever there's a red dot right there,
...that means
...somebody scored it high.
And sometimes when there are two next to each other,
...it means that we both
...really liked it.
KRIS: Not that many.
[laughs]
SVEN: We were very different in our-
KRIS: ...or should we just do, like,
...maybe something like that which is even closer.
SVEN: We should do the ones that we both scored
...enough that it reached 40 points or more.
It's my suggestion.
KRIS: Oh, so on the grand total here.
SVEN: Yeah, on the grand total.
KRIS: Oh, this is one that had... fireworks.
SVEN: Mhmm.
KRIS: I remember this one.
SVEN: I didn't use that line in my scene.
SVEN: the tomahawk thing-
KRIS: The tomahawk?
SVEN: The tomahawk thing.
SVEN: A little weird to me.
KRIS: Yeah.
SVEN: A little bit.
KRIS: It's good, but there i-
...there isn't something that's just like...
...'wow', you know?
SVEN: Yeah, why don't we, like,
...go straight to the top?
Let's see what i- how far do we go?
KRIS: So, like,
...higher than 45 minutes?
SVEN: Higher than 45.
SVEN: I really thought this is gonna, like,
...go far.
KRIS: I like the font.
KRIS: Out of all of the, um...
...Timeless pieces,
...this was probably...
If not the best one but, like...
...top three for sure.
SVEN: I think there are a couple
of really strong Timeless ones.
KRIS: I like the music.
That color grading is killing me a bit.
SVEN: [laughs]
SVEN: We just keep- it's got-
It's been...
...so many hours, and...
We have, like, only so many more hours
...before we need to announce the winner.
So there's no room for politeness.
KRIS: Yeah, I know, we're-
We're way past that.
KRIS: The one with the little girl.
SVEN: Oh, right.
KRIS: Yes.
SVEN: Yah.
KRIS: I like this one.
SVEN: Okay, so we might have to just own it.
...that somebody like]...
did an out of the box.
KRIS: Yeah.
SVEN: thing.
KRIS: So now we're down to the finish line, right?
Like that's-
That's all of them.
SVEN: So the question really is:
Which one...
...does- deserves
...to be picked between those two,
because they're very similar.
KRIS: This shows,
...I think, maybe more editing school.
SVEN: "Mr. White" is not a consideration for you
KRIS: It's too rough, I think.
SVEN: Okay, so it's between this guy and...
...the Italian one.
Although now I feel like I'm leaning
more towards this one, but...
So we got
...this one in the bank.
KRIS: Yeah.
SVEN: Cool.
KRIS: Yeah, let's do that.
SVEN: Alright, so we have a winner.
We have two that tried the same thing,
...and one of them was just better than the other,
...and that's the one that's gonna take the prize
...and win that MacBook Pro and all the other gear.
SVEN: A LaCie 2big Dock drive,
...DJI Copilot,
KRIS: ...Annual Filmstro Premium License
...and 12 months of Adobe Creative Cloud License.
SVEN: That's at least five grand.
KRIS: That's quite the set-up.
SVEN: At least.
And the other one is going to be our first runner-up.
And then...
...we have two more runner-ups,
...and one of them is...
..."Crunchy or Creamy".
That's another The Ever After.
And the third one is...
"Le Mans"
KRIS: Yep.
SVEN: "Le Mans", I'm really happy about this one,
SVEN: ...because I really like-
[laughs]
KRIS: He really fought for it.
SVEN: Congratulations that you won these prizes.
It's awesome,
...but as I started off the video,
...and I want to emphasize this again,
...it's really not about winning the prizes.
It's for you to take the challenge
...to start thinking about storytelling.
We didn't expect that many people to...
...download the footage and cut the scenes,
...and now we're spending, uh...
...into the wee hours trying to
figure out who deserves this prize.
And I hope we- we...
...made the right choice.
But ultimately,
...YOU made the right choice.
KRIS: ]laughs]
That was nice.
That was very clever.
[laughs]
SVEN: I want to thank The Collective
for hosting this competition.
We had, like, this small idea of doing this,
...and we brought it to them and
they're like, "Let's go big with it."
Check out The Collective to really...
...see what else they have going on,
...in terms of other competitions
...and really being a resource
...for filmmakers.
KRIS: You guys are getting these sweet prizes.
It's a good one.
SVEN: And Kris, thank you so much.
KRIS: Yeah.
SVEN: Great collaboration
It's my favorite collaboration
that I did so far on YouTube,
...and what I like about it most,
...I think it goes for both of us, is
...that it involved you not just
watching but actually doing stuff.
KRIS: That was the best part.
I hope we can continue this and
...do more challenges, have
more ways of interacting, and...
...just really engaging with the community
because I think that's something really special.
SVEN: Cool.
Signing off.
Peace.
[laughs]